Guide to the James J. Y. Liu Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
James J. Y. Liu papers
1968-1986
SC0594
Liu, James J. Y.
3.25 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 2000
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biography
James J. Y. Liu, noted scholar in the field of Chinese literature, taught at Stanford University from 1967 until his death in 1986. He served as chairman of the Department of Asian Languages from 1969 to 1975 and, beginning in 1977, held a courtesy appointment as professor of comparative literature.
Liu earned his B.A. at Fu Jen University in Beijing in 1948 and his M.A. at the University of Bristol, England, in 1952. He taught at London University, Hong Kong University, the University of Hawaii, and the University of Chicago before joining the Stanford faculty. He was a Guggenheim fellow in 1971 and a NEH fellow in 1978-79, the same year he received the dean's award for distinguished teaching at Stanford.
Liu was the author of eight books, including The Art of Chinese Poetry, The Poetry of Li Shang-Yin, The Interlingual Critic, Chinese Theories of Literature, and Language--Paradox--Poetics: A Chinese Perspective.
Scope and Content
These papers document Liu's career at Stanford University and include correspondence with colleagues and students, 1971-86; correspondence with publishers and associations, 1969-84; minutes, memoranda, and other records pertaining to departmental and university matters, 1968-85; correspondence and records pertaining to NEH summer seminars he taught, 1976-85; and some curriculum materials such as doctoral reading lists and exams and ditto masters for class handouts, 1969-84.
Correspondents include Frederick P. Brandauer, Kenneth Dean, Eugene Eoyang, Chih-tsing Hsia, Donald Gjertson, Beata Grant, Peter H. Lee, Timothy Light, Irving Lo, Richard J. Lynn, Ronald Miao, Earl Miner, William H. Nienhauser, Stuart Sargent, Donald Shively (Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies), Arnold Toynbee, and Pauline Yu.
Access Terms
Brandauer, Frederick Paul,, 1933-; Dean, Kenneth,, 1956-; Eoyang, Eugene Chen.; Gjertson, Donald E.; Grant, Beata.; Hsia, Chih-tsing,, 1921-; Lee, Peter H.,, 1929-; Light, Timothy.; Lo, Irving Yucheng,, 1922-; Lynn, Richard John.; Miner, Earl Roy.; National Endowment for the Humanities.; Nienhauser, William H.; Sargent, Stuart Howard.; Shively, Donald H., (Donald Howard), 1921-2005.; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Stanford University. Department of Asian Languages.; Toynbee, Arnold,, 1889-1975.; Yu, Pauline,, 1949-; Chinese language--Study and teaching.; Chinese poetry--Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- American Oriental Society, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Art Plus, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Asia Society, 1971-74 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Association for Asian Studies, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- A, 1978-85 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- B, 1974-86 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Canada Council (project assessment), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Center for Research in International Studies (S.U.), 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Chen, Yu-Shih, 1976, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chinese Language Study in Taipei [documents for 1968 meeting] (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Chinese Language Study in Taiwan - transcript of conference proceedings (S.U.), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Chinese librarians' visit, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Chinese linguists' visit, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- CLEAR (Chinese Literature: Essays, Articles, Reviews), 1977-84 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Committee on East Asian Studies (S.U.), 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Committee on East Asian Studies (S.U.) - MA committee, 1977-78 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Committee on East Asian Studies (S.U.) - Steering committee, 1974/75 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Committee on East Asian Studies (S.U.) - Steering committee, 1975/76 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Committee on East Asian Studies (S.U.) - summer grant applications, 1980-83 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Comparative literature, 1973-76 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, in Chinese (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, unidentified (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Council for International Exchange of Scholars, 1974-75 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- C, 1973-74 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- C, 1975-77 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- C, 1978-86 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Department of Asian Languages, 1974/75-1975/76 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Department of Asian Languages, 1976/77-1979/80 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Department of Asian Languages, 1980/81-1981/82 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Department of Asian Languages, 1982/83 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Dictionary of Oriental Literature, 1970-72 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Dissertation proposals, 1978-83 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- D, 1975-84 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- E, 1975-85 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Faculty - memoranda re salaries, benefits, etc., 1975-79 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Faculty grants subcommittee, 1970-80 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- F, 1972-83 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Graduate Students [memos re graduate matters] (Box 3, Folder 8)
- G, 1971-86 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Hawaii, University Press of, 1973-80 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- H, 1972-85 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Indiana Conference (Comparing the Arts: Methods, Terms, Teaching), 1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- I, 1976-83 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Journal of Asian Studies, correspondence, 1973-82 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- J, 1975-85 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Keene, Donald. Modern Japanese Literature (photocopy) (Box 3, Folder 16)
- K, 1973-84 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Lee, Peter H., 1976-85 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Light, Timothy, 1975, 1984-85 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Littauer Foundation, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Liu, James J. Y. Annual faculty reports, 1973-85 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Liu, James J. Y. "Chinese Concepts of Literature" (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Liu, James J. Y. Curriculum vita (incomplete) (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Liu, Wu-Chi and Lo, Irving (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Lo, Irving, 1975-81 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Lynn, Richard J., 1972-77 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- L, 1971-75 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- L, 1976-77 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- L, 1980-86 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Miao, Ronald, 1972-74 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Miner, Earl, 1975-84 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 13)
- M, 1973-79 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- M, 1980-86 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- NEH panel, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- NEH panel, 1974-75 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- NEH panel, 1976-82 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- NEH project review, 1975-76 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- NEH 1976 summer seminar (Box 5, Folder 1)
- NEH 1980 summer seminar (1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 2)
- NEH 1980 summer seminar (2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 3)
- NEH 1985 summer seminar - correspondence (Box 5, Folder 4)
- NEH 1985 summer seminar - sources (Box 5, Folder 5)
- NEH 1985 summer seminar - sources (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Nienhauser, William H., 1979-81 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- N-O, 1972-85 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Pang, Bing-Jun (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Ph.D. exam questions, 1969-81 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Ph.D. reading lists, 1971-84 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Princeton colloquium (Problem of Orthodoxy in Chinese Painting), typescript of his remarks and correspondence, 1969-74 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Princeton conference 1976, correspondence, 1975-76 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- P-Q, 1975-85 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Reprint requests (Box 6, Folder 7)
- R, 1972-86 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Sargent, Stuart, 1976-86 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Stanford University memoranda, 1972-79 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Students, correspondence with or about, 1974-81 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Summer programs (S.U.), 1973-85 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- S, 1972-79 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- S, 1980-85 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Toynbee, Arnold and editors at Thames and Hudson publishers regarding the book Half the World: the History and Culture of China and Japan, 1969-75 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- T, 1971-85 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- U, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Wadham College, Oxford, 1971-75 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Washington, University of, visit, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- W, 1973-74 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- W, 1975-78 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- W, 1980-85 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Yu, Pauline, 1976-83 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- X-Y, 1973-77 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- X-Z, 1980-85 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Ditto masters, 1980-81 (Box 7, Folder 4-8)